<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, preached at St. Marie's in the University of Cambridge May 1st, 1653. Or, An essay to the discovery of the spirit of enthusiasme and pretended inspiration, that disturbs and strikes at the universities: by Joseph Sedgwick, Mr. of Arts, and Fellow of Christs Coll: in the University of Cambridge. Together with an appendix, wherein Mr. Del's Stumblingstone is briefly repli'd unto: and a fuller discourse of the use of universities and learning upon an ecclesiasticall account, submitted by the same authour to the judgement of every impartial and rational Christian.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, Joseph, 1628-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E699_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E699_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R510</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92845)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E699[2] or 108:E699[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, preached at St. Marie's in the University of Cambridge May 1st, 1653. Or, An essay to the discovery of the spirit of enthusiasme and pretended inspiration, that disturbs and strikes at the universities: by Joseph Sedgwick, Mr. of Arts, and Fellow of Christs Coll: in the University of Cambridge. Together with an appendix, wherein Mr. Del's Stumblingstone is briefly repli'd unto: and a fuller discourse of the use of universities and learning upon an ecclesiasticall account, submitted by the same authour to the judgement of every impartial and rational Christian.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, Joseph, 1628-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 57, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.D. for Edward Story, bookseller in Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Do. 1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Episkopos didactikos, Learning's necessity to an able minister of the Gospel" (p. [27]-57) has separate dated t.p. and is filmed separately at reel 108:E.699[3].</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 6.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dell, William, d. 1664. --  Stumbling-stone.</term>
               <term>Universities and colleges --  Sermons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166554:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. LEARNING'S NECESSITY TO AN ABLE MINISTER OF THE GOSPEL.</p>
            <p>By JOSEPH SEDGWICK, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of <hi>Arts,</hi> and Fellow of <hi>Chriſts Coll:</hi> in the UNIVERSITY of <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>R. D.</hi> for EDWARD STORY, Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in CAMBRIDGE, <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:166554:2"/>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:166554:2"/>
            <p>Digniſſimo D<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Procancellario; Collegiorum Praefectis Reverendis, Sociis eorundem doctiſſimis; Iuventuti Nobili, Generoſae, doctae &amp; ingenuae: Academiae Cantabrigienſi, Quam Eccleſia Anglicana Matrem agnoſcit foecundam, piamque Filiam, Reſp. Anglicana ſubditam ſimul ſentit atque etiam Rectricem, Dum in Alumnis aſsidet Reip. Gubernaculo; Dudum denique Orbis Chriſtianus partim reveritus eſt Sociam, partim metuit Adverſariam; Cui cum Sorore celeberrima Veritatem Eccleſia; Conſilium Politia; Lucem omnem, Celebritatem omnem <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſa adeò Anglia unicè refert acceptam: Quam Majorum per aliquot ſecula Pietas &amp; munificentia, Alumnorum ab omni penè hominum memoria ſinceritas &amp; Eruditio Exteris exhibuerunt planè invidendam, Reip. ſtudioſis in pretio ſummo habendam, Et (Quod ſeculo degeneri poſcunt &amp; contendunt Fanatici) Avarae Ignorantiae (niſi Deus coelitùs obnunciaverit) diripiendam: In qua Quod verè culpent nil reperiunt obtrectatores, Monitricibus etiam Avaritia, Invidia &amp; Inſcitia, Praeter hodiernam Academicorum ſcientiam, &amp; eximiam Fundatorum libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem: Crimen eſt Academicis nil aliud, quàm quod Diteſcere videantur &amp; Sapere, ſupra quod par eſt Miniſtris (ſi Deo placet) Evangelicis: Quam à vero crimine ſecuram praeſtitit innocentia, A rapina ſacrilegorum, Dei hactenus Soſpitatoris Tutela, Malevolorum vero diris &amp; calumniis ipſa expoſuit Integritas: (Eorum, inquam, Quibus Ignorare eſt Sanctitatis principium, Quaeque ſequitur Concluſio, Reip. &amp; Eccleſiae pernicies: Qui per ſpiſsiſsimam totius Eccleſiae caliginem tendendum clamant ad lucem Evangelicam, Dei Regno in tenebris conſtituto: Nimirum,</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:166554:3"/>
            <p> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t nocte illa tecti, dum coelum rapere videri cupiunt, diripiant terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>na. Immerito Academiae vitio vertitur talium negligentia, Nam Mater Academia non creat, non violenter ingerit, Sed volentibus excolit ingenia, Et Hos etiam, quod inſe erat, voluit illa fuiſſe doctos.) Eidem Matri Almae aeternitatem apprecans, In eadem Viris pietate, gravitate, &amp; rerum divinarum humanarum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſcientia conſpicuis, Juvenibus Majorum ſplendore, ſuo candore, ſpe omnium Beatiſsimis: (Quos calumniarum impudentiſsimarum in elenchum, Operi praefigit)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Se Suaque L. M. D. D. C. J. S. C. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:166554:3"/>
            <head>To the Judicious and Ingenuous READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a ſtrange Subject, Reader, and in a ſober World, it would be a ridiculous commendation of all-acknowledged Worth. But that Unreaſonableneſs will never receive ſatisfaction, and Errour will be alwayes talkative, and extraordinarily ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceited, if it fancy it hath put all men to ſilence; former Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes might have made this preſent altogether groundleſs and unſeaſonable. I ſuppoſe, when <hi>Ignorance</hi> hath had the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to outbrave a whole <hi>Univerſity,</hi> and ſeemed to plead that its Ingratitude and Turbulency can ſhew the warrant of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſpiration,</hi> I ſuppoſe (I ſay) now gratitude to the place (where I have received a great part of mine education, &amp; might have been a Scholar able to unty as knotty objections, as the enemies of Learning can propoſe) and a just diſcovery of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Revelation, may be ſufficient warrant for this trial of your patience. I think, printing now needs no excuſatory pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. Since I hinder no body from doing the ſame work more ſubſtantially, nor deſire any one to read, that hath any thing elſe to doe, or can tell how handſomely to be idle: I ſhall give no other account of the preſent undertaking, but that it came into my thoughts, (and yet I do not fancy any extraordinary ſpecial motion, though it ran a pretty while in my head,) and why may not I go along with ſo great a croud for noveltie's ſake? If any read it, and diſlike all or any piece of it, it is two to one but I ſhould be of his mind, if I were acquainted with his reaſons. For when all is done, let men talk what they will, Reaſon is an
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:166554:4"/> excellent thing if a man can hit on it. Of all things I can least indure <hi>Enthuſiaſme,</hi> unleſse it be in brave lofty and Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick lines. Then methinks it ſounds rarely, and turned into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Verſe, might be bound up with <hi>Ovid's Metamorphoſis.</hi> Elſe I have no patience to heare in plaine Engliſh and ſober ſadneſs <hi>God made the Authour of lies.</hi> Theſe pretenders to the Spirit ſhould not in juſtice trouble the World with their wild conceptions, till they can ſpeak ſenſe, and make out their Poſitions rationally, or ſhew miracles. And then I ſhall admire, though I be not able to underſtand, what till then I muſt looke upon, as calling in Heaven only to help at a dead lift, and to ſalve over the weakneſs and falſhood, which they are conſcious of; unleſse by a ſtrange ſpirit of deluſion they can think God can be the Authour and diſcoverer of Trifles. Till then I ſhall be bold to eſteeme it no better then non-ſenſe. And, Reader, if you find any ſuch here, I confeſſe it is humane. I gueſſe it is not the firſt you ever have read. Nor is it ſo great a fault, but I dare own, the effect of humane frailty. Only, I am certaine, I intended it for ſenſe. And this is all I can commend the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour or the Work for, that he is a well-meaner, and that this is the ſincerely-intended and thankfull and dutifull endeavour of one, that is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>An hearty honourer of</hi> Learning <hi>and true Worth, where-ever he meets it.</hi> J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:166554:4"/>
            <head>Of the Uſe of LEARNING to the <hi>MINISTERY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Never heard of any that made it a mere If, whither the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities might be improved to a publick Civil advantage, but ſome that knew little what belong'd to good breeding and ingenuous education; that ſcarce remembred that Man was a creature indued with Reaſon, and had faculties higher then corporeall: Men that could not ſo much as ſee that Government and civill Society require much refinedneſſe of parts, and are exceedingly advanced by whatever betters &amp; reſtores the ſoul to any meaſure of its due perfection. I would none would adventure, before they underſtood the terms, to paſſe ſentence upon their connexion. Sure, Languages, Phyſick, and the Mathematicks are more for the vain-glory and empty ſplendour of the Nation: and Civil law muſt be of uſe, till commerce ceaſe, or all other nations be modell'd into the Engliſh form and Conſtitution. It may be eaſily diſcerned by all judicious and ingenuous obſervers, that a great part of the conveniences of this life and neceſſaries to mutuall converſe do owe their invention and perfection to the idleneſſe and luxury of the lazy ſcholars, as ſome are pleaſed opprobriouſly to requite their ſerviceableneſſe and induſtry. In truth, it is a conceit befitting ſuch ſenſuall heads, that there is no pains ſave in ploughing and threſhing; and that Learning gives no help to the Commonalty, becauſe ſuch men are not able to look further then outward appearance. In the Fable the reſt of the Members quarrell'd at the idleneſſe of the Belly; and now the Head it ſeems muſt be cut off &amp; the Eyes pull'd out, as condemned for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>working contrivances and ſloathful direction. Sure, a Watch-maker would count him very ridiculous, that ſhould ſeriouſly rebuke him for curious vanity, and for thoſe ſimple little wheels and ſprings that muſt be hid in the Caſe, while the Hand or the Bell is all that gives our ſenſes notice of the time of the day. Fool, would he anſwer to ſuch pragmaticall and raſh-judging ignorance, theſe are the principal cauſe of that motion which directs you to the hour. And are thoſe men not at all imploy'd to the publick intereſt, who ſpend their time in order to the wel-educating of our Gentry, directing them to thoſe ſtudies which enlarge their parts, ennoble their mindes, and thereby inable them for the more effectuall ſerving their Countries? True learning doth abundantly approve it ſelf and its excellency in many of our former and late eminent Patriots; who
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:166554:5"/> have been as eminent in the ſervice of the State, as in the acquired accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Learning. I leave it to enquiry, how few have been famous for Political Prudence, who have not by ſome after induſtry made amends for the defects or neglect of their education in youth. If any man have abuſed the gifts convey'd to him by the Inſtruction here received, the Commonweale may only ſay of him, as he of an able &amp; conſiderable enemy, <hi>Talis cum ſis noſter utinam eſſes.</hi> &amp; we may heartily wiſh ſuch had diſcover'd themſelves more really for the good of their Native Soil. Do not naturall parts run the ſame hazzard of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>application and miſemployment? yet I ſhall count him either an enemy to the State, or very covetous of company, that ſhould in earneſt pray for a continuall generation of Fools in <hi>England.</hi> An eminent ſouldier (as I think) detracts no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the commendation &amp; deſirableneſs of Martial, skil, though he prove an enemy to his Countrey, and fight valiantly for the diſturbance of its peace. If the enlargement of the ſoul, if the experience of former ages, if the ſervice of the abilities of other men in other ages and nations, if great patterns of eloquent &amp; fit expreſſing our thoughts, if a well-directed judgement inur'd to ſerious &amp; exact ſcanning of things in themſelves and in their circumſtances, if knowledge of men and manners, if a forevers'dneſſe in the conſideration of many caſes of great difficulty and moment, and a readineſſe to draw out what is long agoe prepared, if to be furniſh'd with examples of Divine Providence and humane prudence, if this and farre more then this (which Scholars in publick employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can more ſenſibly and fully explain) be inconſiderable, and have no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the State, I muſt grant that theſe places of publick education are uſeleſſe, and we may without coſt or pains return to an eaſie and cheap Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſneſſe. <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> have hitherto had this reckoned as no mean part of their glory, that they have been friends to learning: and they have admitted Scholars often to the management of publick affairs, yet without any prejudice (to ſay no more) to either of the Republicks. Verily, Learning is diſeſteem'd and vilified by no party, but that which finds it to be moſt of a contrary ſide. I obſerve how even the greateſt enemies of Scholarſhip hugg but one indifferently learned brought over to themſelves, as a main pillar and the conſiderableſt champion of their cauſe. All the countrey too muſt ring of it, if any of them get but a few ſcraps of <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Hebrew.</hi> In Divinity they'l quote as much New-Teſtament <hi>Greek</hi> as they can; and for <hi>Latine,</hi> you ſhall have it as farre as <hi>Luther</hi> and their reading will carry them. Though I am very ſenſible, there may be a diſſembling of Learning, to make ſhew of a Miracle. It is intereſt onely and domeſtick want that makes men inveigh againſt Arts and Sciences, which elſe would by the ſame men be extoll'd as abſolutely requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to a Magiſtrate or a Miniſter. I ſhall adde, that whatever they ſpeak of ſenſe againſt Learning is moſt what borrowed from the ſportfull Exerciſes of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:166554:5"/> Learned Wits in commendation of Ignorance, that ſpeak Sophiſtry beyond theſe mens ſolution, and kick ſuch bladders in play at their pleaſure. It comes likewiſe partly from the melancholy fits of ſome mens devotion, that overlaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly or popularly expreſſe abſolutely what is to be underſtood in compariſon with piety and religion, and that begin to be truly ſenſible of an irreligious adoration of learning, whereof they have formerly been guilty to the contempt and neglect of ſpirituall righteouſneſſe. Something, it may be, is hinted by the diſcontents and railings of a few, that imagine their deſerts not ſufficiently eſteemed and rewarded, and are thence put upon this new device to raiſe their names in the World. For our ordinary Opponents, it would be ſufficient before any rationall judge, truly to alledge againſt their accuſations, that they ſpeak evil of things which they know not. This might very reaſonably invalidate their teſtimony and probations, that they underſtand not enough what learning is, to determine how great its uſefullneſs may be. I ſuppoſe they never had any of their own to try. Nor is the lazy unuſefulneſſe or the abuſe of ſome mens learning any ſtronger argument, then the hoarding up or ſquandring away of money, which ſome men are guilty of, is againſt the true civill uſe of money. Nay, but none make uſe of it but for a vain oſtentation. And yet they may, and as wiſe men as our adverſaries, not be able to diſcerne. I would fain convince men, that onely a learned man is ſufficient fully to diſcover where learning is made uſe of. An ingenuous Artiſt may make uſe of his Mathematicall skill in making a Perſpective, yet an ignorant ſtander by ſees nothing above what an ordinary mechanick may doe: when he ſees the effect of the glaſſe to be extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, he cannot improve it to Mathematicall diſcoveries, nor will eaſily be convinced that thoſe mad ſcrawls in Geometry were the foundation of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the inſtrument. In Diviſion a man may multiply, as he performs the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet ſo indiſcoverably, that one unskill'd in Arithmetick ſees no ſuch matter. In Fortification and like matters, an ignorant man may apprehend things are made as they ſhould be, but not know how farre fetch'd the principles are. A Phyſician may learn out of <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates</hi> to ſpeak plainly, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitely to preſcribe to his patient, and the ſick man be onely ſenſible that he tells him truly of his diſtemper, and doth eaſe him by his preſcriptions. <hi>Tully,</hi> if we may believe himelf, uſed Logick, Rhetorick, and Greek learning, and yet the greateſt part of the Auditory underſtood no more then that he ſpoke their language handſomely, and ſpoke very perſuaſively. Ask <hi>Tully</hi> himſelf or any other Scholar, and they'l ſhew you where <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> was imitated; that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi> the choiceſt Philoſophers and learned Poets were aſſiſtant to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Extemporary diſcourſes may yet be the ſudden workings forth of long &amp; well-digeſted ſtudies. The rule may be plain, the reaſoning very clear, &amp; the action no other then what an ordinary capacity may diſcover to be very pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:166554:6"/> and diſcreet. But conſult Authours, and you may be taught that the rule was grounded upon principles of Philoſophy, the reaſon agreeable to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Art, and the action warranted by ancient examples in Hiſtory. That they ſpeak ſo clearly and intelligibly is according to the rules of learning, and a fruit of their judgements being perfected and throughly informed by Art. It is in other diſcourſes, as it is in ſermons. Common people judge of the Scholar only by high lines and abundance of ſomething which they underſtand not. To knowing men, all this, in a popular audience, is but an argument of one that is very proud of, or afraid to forget that little reading which he hath. The learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſpeaker is more eaſily diſcovered by the plain clearneſſe of his expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the artificiall dependance of his conceptions, in a method and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage proportioned to the capacity of his hearers. Still ſome will urge, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers prove as beneficiall to the Commonweal that are unlearned, and yet as conſiderable in matters of publick concernment. Yet all have not ſuch extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary abilities. He that cannot travail ſo long or ſo faſt as another, if any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect like ſervice from him, he muſt be ſupplied with an horſe. But this will receive farther anſwer, by what follow's hereafter concerning Unlearned Preachers. For the preſent it ſuffices, that, though there ſhould be one or two above all poſſible addition from Acquiſition, yet Learning is ſo farr uſeful to the Nation, as it enables thoſe for publick ſervice whom Nature left to be perfected by Art and Induſtry.</p>
            <p>I hope by this time M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dell</hi> will take it for granted that Learning is of great concernment in Civils. 'Twere charity to think the well-meaning man prevaricates in all his declaiming againſt Learning, or that it is an honeſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, but a ſimple-hearted running too farre on the other hand. His ſenſe and chief intention is, it may be, that learning is not neceſſary to the Miniſtery only; and he complains of the ſcarcity of Secular Foundations in the Univerſity. Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he aims onely to hint that (ſeeing our Colledges are moſt ordered to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and they not enough for a conſtant ſupply of the Miniſtery) beſides far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther care for the increaſe of divine knowledge, it would be a buſineſſe worthy the prudence of our State, and the munificence of ſome noble Benefactours, more to provide for the maintenance of other Profeſſions, and for the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of that learning which is of a Politicall and more Temporall uſefull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: in conformity to the ſuggeſtions of that Noble and judicious Advancer of Learning. If he be offended with this charitable conſtruction, I hope he and others of his perſuaſion will the readilier cloſe with it, when we ſhall in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and main part of our Diſcourſe have examined the Aſſertion they are ſo confident in, That, to a Goſpell Miniſter, Learning, Arts and Sciences are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unneceſſary. But if we ſhould prove it to be helpfull or convenient, the want of ſimple &amp; abſolute neceſſity would be no very ſtrong argument againſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:166554:6"/> the continuance of Colledges and our Schools. Such men would be loath to be ſtinted, as they would ſtint the Church and Commonweale, to the ſhort ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of pure neceſſaries. What their Opinion is in plain Engliſh, it is hard to ſay; it being their cuſtome to involve themſelves and their Auditours in dubious and deceitfull expreſſions. I many times queſtion whether any of them be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their own notions. I have heard M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dell</hi> ſpeak in his way of Of and on, concerning the Saints &amp; Chriſt's union with God: and can at laſt onely ſay, I think he would hold forth Familiſme, i. e, as to this point an Enthuſiaſtick and irrationall kinde of Socinianiſme. When he ſpeaks againſt the Learned Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, ſometimes the epithets of <hi>carnall</hi> and <hi>fleſhly</hi> muſt quite alter the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; then <hi>unuſefull,</hi> and not ſo neceſſary as to exclude in the want; expreſſions quite diſtinct are often one and the ſame. In other men, their arguments give further light to the ſenſe of their poſition, and that at leaſt in proceſſe of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you may ſee what it is they hold. But here the opinion is ſo groundleſſe, and the arguments ſo wilde, that I muſt needs ask, Can the man himſelf tell what he would have? Yet I think it is directly to what he hovers about to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, Whether the Foundations of our Univerſities in the intentions of our pious and magnificent Anceſtours, ſettled (in the greateſt part) for the ſupply of the Miniſtery, for training up there and ſending thence into the ſervice of Chriſt in the Church men furniſh'd with acquired gifts of Learning, be Antichriſtian, or took its originall from the bottomleſſe abyſſe of darkneſſe, or any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall principle; whether this conſtitution be any thing of the Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: and not rather the reſult of pious Wiſdome, well-guided Devotion, and Chriſtian Prudence of men zealous according to knowledge for the promoting of God's glory in the edification of the Church. I mean as to the generall, main and fundamentall intention, though moſt of our Founders might be miſtaken in the particular deſignment, as acting according to the light of thoſe times, when the opinions of the Church of Rome were mixt with the Chriſtian and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Verity of the Weſtern Churches. The Queſtion then ſhall run thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether is it an Inſtitution grounded upon true Chriſtian Prudence, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God and beneficiall to the Church, to provide for the inſtructing in Tongues, Arts and Sciences men naturally endowed with a capacity, and compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent parts, &amp; this in order to the work of the Miniſtery? or is ſuch an Inſtitution Antichriſtian, oppoſite to the Kingdome of our Lord Jeſus, a piece of old igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Superſtition, and therefore unſufferable in a Christian State?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, I think, is the Controverſie between us and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dell.</hi> It is all that need be ſaid to prove an alienation of the Univerſity Lands prejudicial to the Church of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> and conſequently unlawfull, unleſs abſolutely neceſſary for the removall of a greater inconvenience. I heard a ſtory of a French King, as I remember, to this effect. In want of money to maintain an Army, the Church
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:166554:7"/> Revenues being propoſed by ſome of the Councill, ſaith the Pious King, <hi>My Kingdome is not yet wholly drain'd dry.</hi> A ſpeech of a piouſly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly diſpoſed Prince; and that ſavoured more of the Spirit of God and true ſelf-deniall, then the ſpirit that call's upon others to make havock of and deſpoil whatever is devoted to the Intereſt of the Church. I acknowledge mercy to be better then ſacrifice, and the Being of a Nation more conſiderable then the ornamentall ſplendour of the Church. For I apprehend not as yet any ſuch thing ſo ſacred and devoted to a pious uſe, but that urgent and publick neceſſity brings in a ſufficient diſpenſation for any thing beſides the inevitable ruine of a Church. In unavoidable neceſſity of State, when no way elſe can hinder a totall ruine, he is not a true lover of his Countrey, nor hath he dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the brave examples extant in hiſtory, that could not chearfully beg for his Countrie's good, and be ready to ſerve it and the Church in outward want. This leſſon poſſibly others have learn'd, that ſee no ſuch urgency of affairs to invite their own poverty. I queſtion not but (if publick and nationall exigency ſhould force our Rulers to ſuſpend our preſent encouragements to Learning and diligence in the Miniſtery) the Integrity of Univerſity-men and their ſincere deſire to lay themſelves out for the Church, would abundantly appear in their greateſt afflictions; and the more conſpicuouſly by the neglect of many now forward in preaching, becauſe they are forbidden, who would prove as remiſſe, when once they had according to their wiſhes brought about their envious and malicious deſignes againſt Learning and the Miniſtery: a great deal of their vehemency and diligence being from love of diſobedience and contradiction, or a deſigne to overthrow the Clergy. I ſpeake not here of thoſe whom a deſire of enlarging the Kingdome of God, and declaring to others what they have found in his wayes, hath ſtirr'd up to preach unto others: nor do I doubt but there are many ſuch of the Laity. But without any ſpirit of prophecy, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee moſt of our Intruders upon the Miniſteriall office, ſoon after this ſad accompliſhment of their deſires, pretending to be above Ordinances, and very well content to be in the ſilence and eaſe of a more exalted diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis ſhrewdly ſuſpicious that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dell's</hi> conſtancy in preaching would not long ſurvive Tithes and the Univerſity, or ſome ſtipend large enough for a preacher of ſelf-deniall. All is yet but conjecture, for (bleſſed be God) our prudent and worthy Governours are not yet put to ſo dangerous a pitch. And notwithſtanding ſome mens ſuggeſtions of publick profit and Neceſſity, our State will be alwaies ſo conſcienciouſly wiſe, as in the greateſt ſtreights to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how Learning and the Church may be nobly provided for, and whether the pretended Neceſſity doth really counterpoiſe the publick advantage of the preſent Inſtitution, and make amends for the injury that muſt be hereby done to a conſiderable part of the Nation, and the improbability of leaving an able
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:166554:7"/> and well-provided Miniſtery to poſterity. I underſtand not why we ſhould make more bold to leave God to provide by miracle for the Church, then for the State: unleſſe our Faith be of this nature, that where we are really ſenſible of a neceſſity, we are reſolved to ſee our ſelves ſupplied, but we can truſt God very willingly with what we care not much for, and ſcarce believe in truth to have any reallity. But to the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>I heartily deſire that encroaching term of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> (ſo frequent in ſome mens mouths, and uſed even in this buſineſs by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Del</hi> and others) had its unlimited bounds once ſomewhat fixt by aſſigning a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception that might tell us wherein the nature of Antichriſtianiſme conſiſts. It ſeems to me one of thoſe words that have worn out all their ſignification by frequency of being uſed: or elſe onely a nickname to reproach any oppoſer of our private opinions or deſignes. While every thing is Antichriſtian in ſome or others mouths, What ſhould that be (think I) which fits Contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, both parts (for ought I can ſee) as well as one? I ſuppoſe here he meanes what exalts it ſelf againſt the Kingdome of God. but ſtill I am aſmuch to ſeek for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Del's</hi> meaning as before, of which by and by. In the meanetime I ſhall forbeare to urge the Engagements which all Univerſity-men have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into for the defending of the Rights, Priviledges &amp; Honour of our common Mother. Their anſwer is ready: The Oaths were unlawfull, and ſo better broken then kept. Nevertheleſs, what hold can be taken of men that diſannull ſolemne Oaths upon every whimzy? At leaſt, feare of an oath ſhould have put them upon diligent examination and impartial judgement ere they concluded the engagement unlawful. And then (ſeriouſly) they have miſerable Crownes, and very ſoft heads, if theſe be (as it is probable they are) the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Motives which they uſually produce. It is ſomewhat to the purpoſe to propoſe one Queſtion to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dell.</hi> With what Conſcience can any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian knowingly take the wages of Antichriſt? I do not underſtand much honeſty in cheating the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> of his money. Is the Univerſity ſtipend, as paid to a Divine, Antichriſtian maintenance? Then, under what capacity do Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> and his aſſociates enjoy their places in <hi>Cambridge?</hi> I know no account can be given, but that they have ruſht into the Pulpit amongſt a crowd of <hi>Mechanicks.</hi> All (it ſeemes) is fiſh that comes to net. I muſt confeſſe, the ſame largeneſs of Conſcience may beare a man out in receiving the emoluments, where the duty of the place is lookt upon as unlawfull, and in exacting Tithes, which the ſame over and over declares againſt as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daicall</hi> and oppoſite to the Liberty of the Goſpel. It is a ſtrange inconſiſtency of Doctrine and Practice, to extoll ſelf-denial in the Pulpit, and yet to be content to keep the road of the Clergy, that is ſo Antichriſtian, where it leads but to conſiderable profit, But let us ſee how the Opinion will approve it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:166554:8"/> ſelf in ſo high pretences to the motion and powerfull incitations of the Spirit, if theſe Propoſitions be any thing oppoſite to it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Goſpel Miniſtery is to continue, though the extraordinary and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous appearance of the Spirit be ceaſed. For this I believe will be denied in the upſhot, if the truth of our preſent Churches be not the firſt miſtake. Of this we ſhall ſpeak but in ſubſerviency to the preſent diſcourſe. Upon another occaſion, I am ready to declare what I think may be ſaid for a fuller juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Engliſh Churche's Apoſtolicalneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Learning is no hinderance to the advancing of the power of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Gifts of Learning are neceſſary to an able and accompliſht Miniſter or diſpenſer of the Truth of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then, I ſuppoſe, we may adde without much more proof, that the Inſtitutions of Univerſities are not onely commendable, but of extraordinary benefit and (in ſome degree) neceſſity to the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>In all which I ſhall endeavour to take little or nothing for granted, which one in his right wits may conſiderately deny. I know the uſuall way is, Where find you in Scripture that the Apoſtles ſtudied 7 years at the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity? What Word is there for excluding from the Miniſtery thoſe that underſtand not <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine?</hi> If any man applaud ſuch toies, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands no better the Doctrine of Scripture's perfection, I muſt confeſſe I am as much out of hope of convincing him, as free from any feare that he ſhould multiply proſelytes, where any thing of ſober-mindedneſs remaines. I'le ſpeak in a word my thoughts as to the forementioned Doctrine of the fulneſs of Divine Writ, with ſubmiſſion to the better judgements of our Reverend Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church, and to the candid examination of any judiciouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous lover of truth. I underſtand that we reject Traditions, as falſe, when they contradict written Revelation; as dangerous, when the probability of abuſe and ill conſequence overweighs the benefit received by retaining them; but thirdly, the reſt only as uncertaine, becauſe we want much of that evidence which we have of the Scripture's authority. Yet theſe laſt may be retained according to their probability of truth, and uſefulneſs to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of Believers. I ſee no ground to conclude all under falſhood and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane invention, which is not found in the Scripture: though I may rationally queſtion the certainty of ſuch Traditions, any further then I can diſcover their rationalneſs, or then the authority of their diſcoverer and propoſer gives them a credibility. Methinks I ſee theſe Querers acted, I know not how, to a more dangerous conſequence then they themſelves imagine. What uſe is there of their ridiculous Quere's unleſs to weaken the truth of the Scripture's ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency? a ſober and undoubted Truth, if well underſtood, i. e. (as I conceive) as to matters of ſalvation and neceſſary entertainment. though indeed it doth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:166554:8"/> containe all Truths that are certainly of Divine originall. I am afraid this will be the effect among common people, that can ſeldome keep from one of the extremes, if once they be (as they cannot but be in time) ſenſible of this wild way of diſputing from Scripture and by fond and frivolous interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: many of which (though applauded by men as madly conceited as the Enquirers) yet to a ſober indifferent mind evidence but the Authors follies, and unmask that ſpirit of ſcurrility and immorality by which the Contrivers are frequently acted. To this purpoſe we ſhall premiſe theſe Concluſions, of ſome moment in this and other diſputes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Matters of common prudence needed not to be revealed, nor are they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in Scripture; nor is therefore common humane prudence unlawfully uſed in things Eccleſiaſticall. I ſuppoſe it will be eaſily conceived that God never intended that the Church ſhould be a collection of indiſcretion and folly: and hence it is that there are ſo few hints of thoſe things, which mere Reaſon may inſtruct us in. Even in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> diſpenſation, where the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward forme was exactly preſcribed, ſome things were left to common pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and the determination of the Conſiſtory, as indeed it muſt be, when Laws are framed in the greateſt perfection imaginable. I know no other uſe of that which the Apoſtle calls Government 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>i.</hi> an extraordinary gift (as I apprehend) of prudence for the ordering and managing the rule of the Church, and for a particular application of that general direction given by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>all things</hi> ſhould <hi>be done decently and in order.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 40. Decently, and in or according to order muſt be underſtood, according to that becoming ordinateneſs and <hi>decorum</hi> obſerved in the aſſemblies of civile and wel-bred men, without the rudeneſs of immoral and tumultuary meetings. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome (I remember) have expounded by, <hi>according to inſtitution,</hi> i. e. the rule which I gave you. But I think good method, convenient (as it were) ranking is the more uſual ſignification, and beſt ſtands in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. both order and decency being left to the judgement of the Church or its governours, acting according to the rules of prudence. Nor indeed could it be otherwiſe then left thus, if we conſider the ſeverall ſtates of the Church as under and neare to the Apoſtles times, and as in ſucceeding ages. The condition of the Church and Chriſtianity is extreamely varied, being then low, perſecuted, diſcountenanced by the temporal power, and in a ſtate of poverty. Then on the contrary guided by Apoſtolical infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and immediately furniſht from heaven with a large effuſion of the Spirit in gifts and ſpecial endowments. Now remember that the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles is an Hiſtory of the <hi>then</hi> Church, and the Inſtructions given in the Apoſtolical Epiſtles referre to their <hi>then</hi> ſtate, &amp; are to be applied to us onely with conſideration of circumſtances, or in the common reaſon and general duty
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:166554:9"/> contained in them. When I heare ſome mens objections, methinks it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient anſwer to many arguments fetcht from primitive practice; That the Apoſtolical Churche's purſe and power would not carry them out, as in build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Churches and the like. We know they had not then the liberty of publike worſhip. In other things the Apoſtles needed not ſuch helps: yet in times wherein they are needfull, the Apoſtles practice is no prejudice to their uſe. Where read we, ſay ſome, of the Apoſtles praying with all that would come to joine, as the whole Congregation? Neither, ſay I, do we read of a whole Nation profeſſing Chriſtianity, which being now the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal profeſſion of many countries alters the caſe of their and our times. Upon this particular it is not unſeaſonable to wiſh that men would learne ſeriouſly to weigh the ſtrength of their arguments and their extent, more then in relation to their particular queſtion and preſent concernment. It would ſave them the trouble of being forced by others to anſwer their own arguments upon another queſtion. Which hath been very uſual in this very principle, which ſome have formerly upon other occaſions made uſe of, that all is will-worſhip which is inſtituted in the worſhip of God without particular warrant from Scripture: and what the conſequence hath been, our times ſufficiently evidence.</p>
            <p n="2">II. For further confirmation of what hath been ſaid, I obſerve, that there are many things common to a ſociety of Chriſtians and Civil Societies, Churches being humane Societies as to the matter of them. i. partaking of this general nature of being a Collection of rational Creatures: and then what ever is applicable to humane Society in general, belongs to Churches as contained under that larger notion; as for example, the lawfull employment of honeſt wiſdome and diſcretion for its preſervation. Provided onely, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be acted contrary to the principles and nature of Chriſtianity. If this caution be obſerved, rational deductions from Civil Societies, keeping the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of religion, are improveable to the Church. Much more what is dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible from the notion of a Chriſtian Aſſembly.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Where the reaſon of the thing is common and unappropriate to the then-obtaining diſpenſation, and when there is nothing implied to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in the Goſpel Doctrine or Inſtitution; there arguments drawn from the Jewiſh Church do hold good as to the Chriſtian. It is warranted by S. <hi>Paul's</hi> diſcourſe about Goſpel maintenance for the Miniſtery. For the Church then, was a Society joyning in the ſervice of God; that and this partaking in the general notion of a religious Aſſembly, their Miniſtery of a Miniſtery, and their Worſhip of the Worſhip of God. And obſerving the difference of their and our diſpenſations, we may very lawfully make uſe of their inſtitutions to direct us to diſcover many things, which belong to religious Congregations, Officers and Worſhip in generall. That onely being abrogated of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:166554:9"/> which was typical, and founded in God's Covenant with Iſraelites as Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. i. e. as inſtated in the land of Canaan, not as men, and related to God by creation and the covenant of nature.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Which follows from and may adde ſtrength to what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid: Collections from Scripture, though not to every eye expreſt in Scripture, and arguments drawn according to the different circumſtances of the Primitive and Later conditions of the Church, are proofs very admittable by any ſober Chriſtian. This is no more then what reaſon readily grants, as founded in the very nature of the things. no more then what is commonly allowed as ſufficient proof in collecting from any Hiſtory, ancient Cuſtome and uſage, or old Law, which is in force with reſpect to the alteration of times. It is that which in other more uncontroverted caſes is uſed in alledging of Scripture it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Cuſtome and practice of the Church in ſucceeding ages, and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Hiſtory, eſpecially neare the Apoſtles times, univerſal, and in conformity to the former preſumptions, is an argument in it ſelf as conſiderable, as intolerable to Enthuſiaſtick Spirits or men that affect novelty &amp; their own humours. Now to our queſtion; The Chriſtian Schooles in former ages are notorious, and the high price then ſet upon Learning is cleare by their diligence in inſtructing their children in Arts and Sciences, and by the ſenſe they had of <hi>Julian's</hi> inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious forbidding them the Heatheniſh Learning, and denying them the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the then Schooles of literature. What joy for their deliverance from this oppreſſion by his death? What induſtry in ſupplying the want of publick education? It is evident <hi>Nazianzen</hi> had other thoughts of humane Learning then thoſe that prefer <hi>Julian</hi> for a pattern of reformation. But this way of arguing, were I skill'd in it, would be put off with the Antiquity of the Myſtery of Iniquity, which (if we believe ſome) had almoſt in every thing overſpred the Church of Chriſt ſtraight after the deceaſe of the Apoſtles. Indeed it would be ineffectuall, becauſe beyond the poſſibility of our Opponents Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, who have expreſt their Chriſtian juſtice in vilifying and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Ancients, whom they are not at all acquainted with. Yet it needs no great reading to know that thoſe which we acknowledge to be the times of greateſt Apoſtacy in the Church, were the freeſt from ſecular Learning, and had as much darkneſs in that reſpect as our Adverſaries can hope to bring <hi>England</hi> to, if the Univerſities were utterly aboliſh'd. The Reformation of Religion and the reviving of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in plaine Engliſh, the Gentile Learning, were contemporary, and happily promoted by the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments. And it were ſtrange if the Reformation begun in knowledge, could no otherwiſe be carried on then by returning to the Ignorance of darker and more degenerate ages, What can an adverſary to the reformation in reaſon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:166554:10"/> think elſe, but that they have convinced us of the inſufficiency of our Cauſe, and that now we are ſenſible Learning was onely an argument for us, when our Opponents had not attained to enough to diſcover our fallacies, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures &amp; learned juglings? What greater triumph can the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> deſire, then to ſee us beat out of our confidence of Learning, and put to a poore and irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſhift of private infallible Inſpiration? One inclining to <hi>Atheiſme</hi> will be perfectly poſſeſſed that the defences of Chriſtian Religion were only proud triumphs over the too unexerciſed diſputers againſt it in <hi>Heatheniſme,</hi> or that the power of the Chriſtian Emperours was the ſtrongeſt argument for the truth of Chriſtianity: Experience having (as he may juſtly ſurmiſe if all Chriſtians were of theſe mens minds) diſcovered to our ſelves the weakneſs of our Religion, unable to withſtand the clearer light of natural and refined reaſon.</p>
            <p>We come now to our former Concluſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion</hi> I. A Miniſtery was not to ceaſe with the primitive times and Apoſtolical adminiſtration and gifts. Which will be proved if in particular we evidence the truth of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the lawfulneſs of its Miniſtery: which may be done thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a viſible Church of God in <hi>England,</hi> or the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> is a true Church of Chriſt in an Apoſtolical ſenſe. By a Church I mean, according to the notion of a Church in the Apoſtolical writings (to which I refer any attentive reader for proof of the notion) I meane (I ſay) by a Church, a Collection or Society of men united in the Worſhip of God in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, whom they profeſſe to believe to be ſent by the Father for the remiſſion of ſinnes, and according to whoſe precepts they engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to lead their lives in hopes of everlaſting life through the ſame Lord Jeſus. Though as yet, they are no otherwiſe renewed then by this more generall belief of the Goſpel and Salvation promiſed by Chriſt. i. e. but poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and <hi>in gradu remoto</hi> ſanctified, their lives being unanſwerable to their profeſſion and promiſe. And this is the caſe of the Engliſh communion, whoſe members having been baptized in their infancy, and having at yeares of diſcretion acknowledged their aſſent to the then-dedication of them to God, and acknowledging their Baptiſme into repentance for remiſſion of ſins, are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Saints by call, called unto holineſs, and true members of the Church, till duly and juſtly put out of communion. This is in Apoſtolical phraſe a Church of God, and a Congregation of Believers, in the Scripture expreſſion. And that is ſoberer language then <hi>carnal</hi> and <hi>worldly</hi> Church. though there is a more inviſible Church, more ſpiritually and intimately united to Chriſt, to which neither hypocrites nor unrighteous profeſſours do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long: the bounds of it being narrower, and ſalvation attainable to none that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:166554:10"/> are without it. But the Church we ſpeak of is ſuch as thoſe S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to, viſible and externall, the conditions of whoſe communion was in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time but a believing Chriſt to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and ſubmitting to Baptiſme to the remiſſion of ſinnes, and repentance from dead works. This Church is not to be reſted in; neither are the members of it to be vilified and ſlighted as out of the Church, as unbelievers, or to be debarr'd communion, who have the faith of Chriſt in them, and whoſe hearts God hath purified by a belief wrought in them of the truth of the Goſpel, though their faith be dead, as yet unprofitable, and that which, unleſs it be brought into act and work by Love, will not ſave. Yet there is that faith wrought in them by the Spirit of God in their education, which may by the aſſiſtance and ſupervenient grace of the Spirit be a foundation of reall cloſing with Chriſt, and real Goſpel-holineſs. In the meanetime God hath purified their hearts by this Faith which is in them (though unconſidered, unimproved, and unactive) in that ſenſe as I think is agreeable with the context of <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 9. (i. e.) ſo that though they were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure as to legal purification, uncleane and profane as to communion with the worſhippers of the true God, God hath now made them cleane as to Church-communion, and being admitted into Brotherhood by the believing Jewes, by bringing them to a belief that Jeſus is the Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Further to warrant the communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> obſerve, that thoſe that are united in the Faith of Chriſt, ought to be united in Church-communion. i. e. ought to aſſemble together for the publick Profeſſion of their Faith in Chriſt and joint ſerving of God, ſeeking him for each other and the cauſe of Chriſt in enlarging and protecting his Church, and for mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual edification. It is grounded upon that promiſe of our Saviour, <hi>He that confeſſes me before men, him will I confeſſe.</hi> 'Tis true, there are other wayes of confeſſing Chriſt: but the promiſe is to confeſſion in the latitude, and it is dangerous in any particular to be guilty of denying Chriſt. Aſſembling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to the imploring of Divine grace; and a thankfull remembrance of the Lord till he come, is the duty of the members of Chriſtian Churches: the ends ſtill remaining, and being as neceſſary as in the Apoſtles times, <hi>viz.</hi> to hold out the profeſſion and faith of Chriſt to the World, and to ſtrengthen, encourage and build up each other in our moſt precious faith and Chriſtian love, which is mightily confirmed by our union in the ſervice of God, and which is the ground of God's eſpecial regard to united prayers, which argue the unanimity and concord of his people. The arguments againſt our aſſemblies, that of mixt-congregations being anſwered in the precedent aſſertion, are theſe two: I. The perfection to which ſome men have attained ſo as to be paſt thoſe beggarly rudiments, externall and fleſhly worſhips &amp;c. and now to live in immediate communion and a conſtant Sabbath. If this glory and raiſedneſs
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:166554:11"/> be reall in them, more then fancy &amp; words. I ſhall only ſay, Firſt, humility and ſelf-diſeſteeme is one maine piece of a Chriſtian's perfection. Secondly, ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Divine inſtitution certainly would be no derogation from happineſs; yea, that is the queſtion. And for proof of it we appeale to Apoſtolical pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, &amp; thoſe firſt times wherein this ſpirit was wholly unknown. We deſire not a warrant from Scripture, to beare us out in our inconformity to this primitive practice. though we might more reaſonably, then they require of us, to ſhew by Scripture that the effuſion of the Spirit in extraordinary gifts ceaſed with the firſt age of the Church. The matter is quite other, in man's duty, and God's free diſpenſation. Eſpecially, if we remember that a publick profeſſion of our dependance upon God, and communion in ſeeking and acknowledging of God, are the dictates of natural light, and indiſpenſable. Thirdly, enquiry may be made whether they are incapable of growth and beyond all increaſe of grace; if not, whether the Scripture-way of edification be not moſt imitable. Fourthly, ſuch glorious Saints in reality, might aſſemble to the greater benefit of inferiour Chriſtians: (and ſure no perfection priviledges from ſerving God in building up the Church.) Fifthly, to acknowledge God and Chriſt before men, to bleſſe him for his mercies, to glorify him in the Congregations of his Saints, nay to celebrate the memoriall of his death in the Supper of our Lord, are Duties agreeable with the moſt Saintlike eminency, while converſant in the World. The moſt glorious Saint or Angel, if in a body and mixt with humane ſociety, would, I believe, thus be employed, and count it no diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, no ſuperfluous or empty ſervice. Methinks the ſouls under the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and the <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> reſounding from Heaven to the Apocalyptical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, are good preſumptions that there is ſome ſuch thing in Heaven; or that ſuch ſervice is not altogether indecorouſly attributed to the higheſt manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God. But I wiſh there be nothing of ſelf-conceit, impatience under God's wiſely-and-juſtly-ſuſpended communication of himſelf, or formality converted to another extreme, at the bottome of this high-towring confidence. I deſire in my ſelf to be ſhrewdly ſuſpicious of that Heaven, which leſſens my willingneſs to meet God and his Angels (it is as probable an expoſition of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. as any I have heard) coaſſembled with believers upon earth. An heart enlarged to communion with Saints, to edification of our brethren, to a conſtant praiſing of God, and to an embracing of any opportunity of acknowledging thankfully before men and Angels the love of God in our Redemption; an heart, I ſay, thus raiſed to be <hi>Praecentor</hi> in the Quire of the Saints bleſſing God the Father and our Lord Jeſus, is an heaven in almoſt every thing but in the ſpiritualneſs and Immortality of the Body. II. The imperfection of our aſſemblies in compariſon of the primitive times is to ſome an argument againſt our Worſhip of God. Indeed, it is a good argument to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:166554:11"/> quicken our dulneſs to an imitation of their affectionate fervency. Yet I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the experience of devout ſouls, whether God be wholly abſent from our aſſemblies, and the quickning preſence of the Spirit abſolutely withdrawn. We retaine not empty and dead Ordinances: and to call them but dead and ineffectuall ſhadowes is an expreſſion injurious to the manifeſtations of God in many a faithful heart, who can ſenſibly and with rejoycing beare witneſs to the appearance of God in our publick Service. What wants of miraculous preſence, we may referre to the Divine Wiſdome manifeſting it ſelf ſuteably to each Age of Chriſtianity. What wants of effectualneſs, let us blame our negligence, and approach more ſpiritually to ſervice. But what conſequence is it? (We are already by much ſhort of the primitive ardour, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt ſtill more recede from their ſo glorious example) While we believe the Goſpel grace worth our thanks, while we need his aſſiſtance and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, we muſt not deny God the ſervice that is due unto him even by right of Creation; but do it to our beſt ability. Expect what glorious times you ſee ground for in Scripture. I ſhall not quarrel though the largeneſs of your hopes may exceed any promiſe I can ſee in Divine Writ: yet remember to preſſe toward it in eminency of piety and due attendance upon the Worſhip of God, which I am ſure can be no greater prejudice to the drawing nigh of any glory in the Church, then <hi>Simeon's</hi> waiting in the temple was to his ſeeing of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There muſt be ſet over the Church men that may watch to the Flock, Paſtors &amp; Teachers, men able to inſtruct, direct and order the Church of Chriſt, and more eſpecially in their religious Aſſemblies. All were taught of God and had the unction of the Spirit in the Apoſtles times, aſmuch certainly as in ours. yet ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 3, 4, 22. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11, 12, 13. Hath not the Church need of edification now? Is exhortation, conſolation, ſtirring up and quickning to duty now altogether needleſſe? If the Churches planted by the Apoſtles, and in preſence of whom the power of God had appeared ſo miraculouſly ſtood in need of Overſeers and Inſtructours; I leave it to any rationall man to judge what is requiſite in theſe remoter ages. We acknowledge (will our Adverſaries anſwer) our wants. but we muſt not be guilty of will-worſhip and our own inventions in the worſhip of God. We expect, ſay they, this Miniſtery; only ſay we, it hath for the preſent ceaſed; and we dare not intermeddle of our ſelves in the things of God. In reply to this, I muſt premiſe that I ſpeak of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church chiefly, let thoſe defend themſelves that have withdrawn from its communion and erected Churches of other models. Then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath not created a new Miniſtery, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued it ſucceſſively from the Apoſtolicall Age. Onely its Paſtours, being for Conſcience excluded the Roman communion, have (as duty to God and their Saviour bound them) aſſembled together for the ſervice of God, and inſtituted ſtill freſh Paſtours in the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:166554:12"/> 2. The notion of Will-worſhip is very probably vindicated from miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion by <hi>Doctour Hammond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To provide by Chriſtian prudence, in imitation of Apoſtolical wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for the Churches good is not Will-worſhip. It is a ſtrange ſtate for Chriſtians under the Goſpel, and worſe then under the Law, if they are plac'd in ſuch a condition, as that they muſt almoſt inevitably be guilty either of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the commands of God, or inſtituting ſomething of their owne heads. To me (under pardon) this ſeems to be the Goſpel frame, as to Church affairs, that it is delivered from that punctuall legality of the former diſpenſation; and proceeds onely according to the naturall rules of Divine Worſhip and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an prudence. It is too, very improbable that the Providence of God hath left all theſe Ages of the Church, ſince the Apoſtles, without any means of a Goſpel-miniſtery.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our publick Miniſtery can ſhew their warrant in the hearts of many of their hearers, from that Spirit which gives no atteſtation to Antichriſtian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It is my private opinion, and therefore propoſed to a ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: It may be, the duty of a Miniſter is no other, then what may be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without miraculous gifts, and is indeed the duty of every Chriſtian, if he had proportionable abilities, and as farr as may conſiſt with order and decency in the Church. Our Miniſters pretend not infallibly to deliver the will of God, any further then it is delivered in Scripture in undoubted plainneſſe; much leſſe do they bring a new Goſpel or a new Revelation into the World. There is the difference between them and the Apoſtles, as the Jewiſh Lawgiver and the Expounders of the Law. <hi>Moſes,</hi> as the Apoſtles, was infallibly guided: not ſo the Expounders of the Law. The office of a Miniſter is wiſely to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the Church, to ſearch into the will of God revealed already, declare, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and preſſe the Truths already divulged by the Apoſtles. The ſeparation of their calling is (beſides that diſorder muſt be avoided, and it is very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that the gifts of thoſe be approved to the Church, who take upon them the charge of inſtructing others) it is, I ſay, becauſe all are not gifted for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, it will (if conſcienciouſly performed) take up the greateſt part of their time, and by the neceſſary means at preſent of enabling themſelves for this imployment, they are taken off from a capacity of providing for themſelves in a ſecular way: being trained up quite contrary to the waies of trade and worldly trafficking.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion</hi> II. Acquired gifts are no hinderance to the Kingdome of God. Not to the embracing of the Goſpel and apprehending the Myſteries thereof; nor to a Goſpel Miniſter. S. <hi>Paul</hi> was well vers'd in Jewiſh and Graecian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature, and mixeth pieces of Poetry with his ſacred conceptions. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:166554:12"/> ſaith indeed, <hi>Not many wiſe.</hi> But Knowledge puffing up with pride, and ſo puniſh'd with ſpirituall blindneſſe, ſpeaks nothing to the diſadvantage of Knowledge. <hi>Not many rich and noble,</hi> is as much Scripture. I wiſh there be not as viſible characters of pride in the ſelf-eſteem and cenſoriouſneſſe, and the ſpirit of turbulency of our Adverſaries. I am confident Learning is no enemy to any honeſt intereſt of Truth or true Chriſtian piety. If they mean by the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God any thing beſide what S. <hi>Paul</hi> means, or then that righteouſneſſe, peace and joy in the Holy Ghoſt, which he ſpeaks of, if they pleaſe to explain themſelves, it may be it is a commendation to Learning that it proves an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ſome phantaſticall whimzy or baſe deſigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion</hi> III. Gifts of Learning are neceſſary to an accompliſh'd diſpenſer of the Word of God. Our Adverſaries make much uſe of the Epithets <hi>Secular, Humane</hi> and <hi>Naturall.</hi> And then how popular a conviction is it to deſcant upon God's not ſtanding in need of man's help, upon the Kingdome of God its being ſpirituall, divine and ſupernaturall? Now all is done: only they might confirm the antiquity of their Monkiſh ſpirit out of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibarbarus.</hi> But are not a good voice and good lungs naturall? God ſtands not in need of Miniſters or their Learning, yet may be pleaſed to make uſe of both, and may require it in his ordinary diſpenſation with the Church. Learning though fetch'd from an Heathen may be from the authour of Truth, and in a Chriſtian ſubſervient to the work of the Goſpell. Is onely ſecular Learning taught in the Univerſities? Doth not the ſearch into Divine Revelation take up a great part of Univerſity-ſtudies? To ſpeak more clearly to this main aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, I ſhall take notice of theſe propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Smattering in Learning is altogether uſeleſſe, and good for nothing but to fill up the period with a frivolous ſentence in Latine, that is too ſimple to be ſpoke in plain Engliſh. None ever ſaid that the conning by heart a few Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call terms and Philoſophicall diſtinctions, without any conception correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the minde, was any benefit to ſacred ſtudy. And here ſome of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries may ſee the miſtake in their own experiment. Their Learning and unconcocted Philoſophick crudities ſtand them in no ſtead in expounding the Bible &amp; opening difficulties in Divinity. Nor can they, I ſuppoſe, defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a ſword, unleſſe they have it fully in their hand: and yet a ſword is a very needfull weapon. He muſt have faſt hold of Learning and have it perfectly at command, that intends to make any uſe of it in Divinity or Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity. Do theſe men conclude a Medicine ineffectuall, becauſe they have without ſucceſſe applied it before it was prepared? When we ſay a knife is uſefull in cutting, 'twere madneſſe to alledge to the contrary that I have tri'd an unſharpened &amp; rude piece of ſteel. Yea, but we can preach as well as the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt. It may be, to your own apprehenſions, and men as little able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:166554:13"/> as your ſelves. But let me anſwer in this homely but pat ſimilitude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Meat may be gnawn or pull'd in pieces, but it is a very ſlovenly carving to others. And I cannot ſee but it is Chriſtian wiſedome to avoid all juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of contempt to the preaching of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is eaſie to give our what another hath carved to our hand. Sermon notes and printed Sermons may carry a man very farre. And I have been cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly informed, that printed Sermons got by heart ſerved a great while an Iriſh Apoſtle for an appearance of mere depending upon the ſudden ſuggeſtions of the Spirit. But, Sirs, your Authours were Scholars. Now I ſhould be very loath to have him for my guide that wholly uſeth another man's eyes, &amp; takes up all upon truſt. Methinks a double danger of fallibility is too much. The firſt had his miſtakes, and it is probable this ſecond will return them with ſome addition of his own, miſtaking him that miſtook. I like a directer that is able to judge ſomething of himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Many meats need not a knife. Yet there are ſome Truths of very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable import, that carry difficulty, and if explained amiſſe, may be of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence to a godly life.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Naturall parts, uſe and practiſe may in many men make a great ſupply for the want of acquired parts; and exceed an induſtrious incapacity or an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exerciſed ſtudiouſneſſe. And this is in plain Engliſh what ſome men call the extraordinary aſſiſtance of the Spirit in prayer and preaching. Many of the Laity are men of quick and ready abilities, nimble wits, ready apprehenſion, and clear volubility of language in expreſſing their conceptions: eſpecially ſome having been conſtant hearers of the Miniſtery, and by much exerciſe in preaching, praying and diſcourſing of matters of Divinity, have accuſtomed themſelves to nimbleneſſe of head and tongue. Now becauſe theſe poſſibly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell many a dull Plodder (whom neceſſity, unfitneſſe for any thing elſe, or his parents fond and ignorant admiration have quite againſt Nature's intention, caſt upon the Univerſity) or ſome few who have injured their naturall abilities by intangling themſelves altogether in ſcholaſticall intricacies; preſently, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, <hi>Deus è machina,</hi> a Miracle, and the Spirit is come upon them from above. But</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take them out of their road, from ſome general Doctrines of Chriſtianity, to a particular explication of Chriſtian Truths and Duties.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What would they have proved if learned education had ſeconded na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or been laid as the foundation of their exerciſe? It is pitty they ſupplied not the places of ſome others in the Univerſities.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is all equity and juſtice to ſet them in compariſon with men of like parts and equall practiſe: and then judge who hath the advantage.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What groſſe miſtakes are they guilty of often in interpretation of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:166554:13"/> and collection thence, for want of skill in the Original, and artificial diſcourſe?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider, theſe men would have excell'd others in a Trade, and I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe without <hi>Aholiab's</hi> inſpiration. We find the ſame effects in many unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, who by practice and natural ſagacity judge clearly, and expreſſe themſelves aptly and fluently in matters of civil diſcourſe and intercourſe.</p>
            <p>Natural ability is the gift of the all-governing Spirit, and the ability acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by exerciſe is the bleſſing of God: but all this is nothing of the gift of the Spirit in an Apoſtolical ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Experience and ſenſe of the wayes of God, or true reall inward grace, is a great advantage to a Miniſter of the Goſpel: but not a neceſſary indiſpenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able requiſite, not alone a ſufficient qualification. Indeed experience addes life, heat and affectionate power to the delivery of the Word. But ſtill the coldneſs and deadneſs of an unſanctified Preacher is oft-times diſcernable only to himſelf. Upon equality of all other conditions an experienc'd Chriſtian is able with more vigour to declare the Truths of Chriſt. So he may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Preacher more ſenſibly then he underſtands himſelf. A dumbe man and a ſtammerer may underſtand mine exact and true relation better then my ſelf, becauſe concerned in the action, and preſent to that which I deliver upon diligent enquiry and information received from others. Beſides the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Senſe oft-times confounds the Underſtanding and Elocution: ſith one may feel ſo as to put expreſſion to a loſſe: and then though I apprehend an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary affection in the man, I may be to ſeek for a true explanation of the cauſe. Every one that can fight well, I think, is not fit to write or Tacticks or the Hiſtory of a Warre: both which have been well done by men who never engaged in any military ſervice. A man may feel abundance of paine, and yet an Anatomiſt may be able more diſtinctly and rationally to mine under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to explaine what part is affected, and how. But, you'l ſay, affection is more popular and likely to breed affection. Yet, there are ſome whoſe judgements muſt be convinced, and that may deſire a rationall explication. And ſure clearneſs of knowledge is a very good foundation for the permanency of affection. To cleare this propoſition yet more, I obſerve</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Apoſtles rules require unſcandalouſneſs of life in a Miniſter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Chriſt's ſending out of <hi>Judas</hi> is ſufficient ground for calling to and receiving into the Miniſtery men of abilities, whom we have no preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of in regard of reall grace. See <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 2. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> teaching of truth are to be heard: and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> joyes in the Goſpel's being preach'd, though out of a principle of Contention, which is no fruit of the Spirit dwelling in a Preacher. Grace is for the uſe of a man's ſoul, Gifts for the uſe of the Church. The confuſion of the Spirit as working
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:166554:14"/> grace, and as pouring forth gifts is a fundamental miſtake in this queſtion. But know that a Miniſter and a Chriſtian are diſtinct notions. And though the ungracious Preacher doth not ſo much as think of a bleſſing upon his work: yet the Church and a conſciencious hearer may believingly expect fruit and edification from God in and by his Miniſtery, whom God may ſanctify as to the Church and its benefit, though in his private reſpect he neglect him. So <hi>Cyrus</hi> of old was ſanctified for the uſe of Iſraël: and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſuppoſes that he that preaches to others may himſelf prove a caſt-away.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all things delivered in the Goſpel, and neceſſary to be explained are not experienceable. Withall, conſequent experience of joy or dutifull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is not ſufficient ground of Truth. It is no improbable ſuppoſition that two really godly may both rejoyce in the Lord: the one for the univerſal extenſiveneſs of his Goodneſs; and the other for the ſpeciall diſtinguiſhingneſs of his Love. Yet whether's experience ſhall warrant the truth to be on his ſide?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Experience being private and particular (of particular caſe, conſtitution and arbitrary actings of the Spirit of Wiſedome) is not to be extended to general rule, without ground in Scripture or the nature of the thing. Elſe the new-experienc'd-Divinity argued conſequently againſt the benefit of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and to other mens formality in the uſe of them, from ſome mens own experience of their hypocriſy in duty, and their receiving no good by them through their default and God's juſtice.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Shall I adde, That Duties are to be delivered above the ſhortneſs of our own attainments? Duties as delivered in Scripture, and therefore as they are to be preſt, exceed our experience. But, ſome will ſay, we have ſome degree of experience, and from that collect what is yet above us. I anſwer, So one as yet unexperienc'd apprehends in part: ſome kind of knowledge being preſuppoſed to experience. Then ſecondly, a notional knowledge is ſufficient to a verball declaration: and may in many things be clearer and ſafer, while it follow's Scripture-revelation, other mens manifold experience, though not its own.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Gifts and endowments are principally requiſite to a Goſpel Miniſter, as ſuch. For the nature of a Miniſter is office &amp; employment; and what enables to be a Chriſtian, enables not to the function of a Miniſter. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. peruſe the whole chapter. To cleare up this, conſider</p>
            <p n="1">1. The gifts of the Spirit in the Apoſtles times were not onely for a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous confirmation of the Doctrine's Divine Original, and for a teſtimony of their deſignation to the work of planting the Goſpel, but for enabling them to their work. Tongues indeed, S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, were for unbelievers; but prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was for believers and their edification. Indeed the miraculous way of conveyance and the wonderworking power, was partly for atteſtation to the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:166554:14"/> truth of Chriſtian revelation. But withall they were enabled for the carrying on the work of the Goſpel by gifts given from above. To be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1. able as well as willing to teach, was the condition of a Biſhop in S. <hi>Paul's</hi> time. and he exhorts to ſeek gifts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 1. Then there was the Holy Unction, and that not needleſs. By the way I ſhall propoſe to examination, whether S. <hi>John's, Ye have received the anointing,</hi> may not relate to this enablement of the primitive Paſtours and Teachers: and ſo be far enough from concluding any unneceſſarineſs of a Miniſtery. For S. <hi>John</hi> writes againſt Falſe Apoſtles, and may very probably be thought to direct his Epiſtle to the Chriſtian Churches, as a collection of Paſtours and people. Ye need not (ſaith he) any new Inſtructer, new Revealer, or explainer of revelation, ſince you have among you in your Churches the Divine <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> and the Spirit of God directing and enabling your Presbytery conſtituted by Apoſtolical Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. You have received, is very true, though every individuall member of the Church had it not, but by intereſt in the Paſtours. But let the able judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Gifts and enablements are as neceſſary, nay more, now then then. There is the ſame need of inſtructing, reproving and convincing of gain-ſayers, demonſtrating the truth of the Goſpel by Scripture, and anſwering objections againſt it. Beſides that our remoteneſs from the Apoſtles (who in difficulties might then be readily conſulted) and the ambiguity eſſential to the plaineſt writings, with the ſeverall prepoſſeſſions and conceptions of ſeverall parts of Chriſtians, have made the controverſies in Divinity almoſt infinite. Due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, good judgement, and all imaginable accompliſhments are little enough to direct in what is to be preached for the truth of God; and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh Scripture and Catholick Verity from private conceits and upſtart opinions. For the teachings of the Spirit, they are ſo diverſe in ſeverall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders, ſometimes ſo unagreeable to the true meaning of the Word, that we are very well ſatisfied in the neceſſity of S. <hi>John's</hi> advice, to try the Spirits. Conſider the Apoſtles ſpeake not in our naturall language, and many paſſages relate to cuſtomes now obſolete and Hiſtory of thoſe times not mentioned by any Inſpired Writer. Do not ſome proofs from the old Teſtament ſeeme to proceed upon ſome then-received traditional expoſitions?</p>
            <p>The gifts then neceſſary to the preaching and explaining of the Goſpel (as ſo) are ſtill as neceſſary to that office, and the more for the ceaſing of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Heathens now muſt be convinced by rational evidence of the Divinity of our revelation. Doubtleſs, in this age Learning is neceſſary, when <hi>Atheiſme</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to creep up in the Church and to our-face Chriſtianity. And how nearely related <hi>Atheiſme</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſme</hi> are, and how ſubſervient each to other, is well obſerved by that judicious and faithfull ſervant of God and the Truth, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>More,</hi> in his preface to that moſt effectuall <hi>Antidote againſt Atheiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:166554:15"/> 3. Acquired gifts are many of them for ſubſtance the ſame with thoſe then conferr'd by the Spirit. The revelation of the matter by them then publiſh'd, we have in our ſacred Records; and 'twere as ration all for theſe men to bid us expect the Goſpel truth too in an extraordinary way of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. What we read is what the Apoſtles preach'd, and our Miniſters (as the then-Teachers) preach according to the ſound or ſaving forme of words delivered to them by the Apoſtles, now in writing, as then alſo by word of mouth. The other enablements given to them as preachers and publiſhers of this doctrine for enabling them in their duty, were but the raiſing and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting their naturall faculties in order to clearing up the truth to themſelves and others. And this is the deſigne and effect of a great part of Learning. Indeed if naturall parts be neceſſary to a Miniſter, let our Adverſaries under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that <hi>Logick, Metaphyſicks</hi> and <hi>Rhetorick</hi> are but rectifiers and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecters of naturall endowments; and then tell us, why the perfecting and rectifying of natural parts is uſeleſs and unneceſſary. I am bold to repeate, that the maintainers of this diſpute againſt Learning, underſtand not what it is, but judge by their own undigeſted notions &amp; rude ſhadows of Learning.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Acquired gifts are the gifts of the Spirit, though not from its mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous operation. Studiouſneſs and a bleſſing upon it are the gifts of Divine Providence in the World and eſpecially in the Church. Sure the diverſe way of conveyance, and the difference of ordinary and extraordinary vary not the nature of the things. What was created by God, produced ſtill after its kind, though here was generation inſtead of creation. It is ſtrange the gracious gifts of God ſhould looſe their eſteeme, becauſe they are not beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a way of miracle.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Miraculous gifts were given upon account of the Apoſtles exigency. It pleaſed God in his wiſdome to make uſe of the ſimplicity and unlearnedneſs of the Apoſtles: and that to magnify his great power, in thoſe miraculous abilities infuſed into them from Heaven. So God choſe <hi>David</hi> from a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard to be King, and furniſh'd him with Kingly abilities. Yet is this a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to chuſe Governours of the meaneſt condition and knowledge, becauſe God is able to give them the ſpirit of Wiſdome and Government? That miraculous gifts are ceaſed, for ought I can heare, is yet very palpable. Amongſt us that are Chriſtians, two reaſons may be given. Firſt, unbelief is ceaſed. The Faith of the Goſpel is become a preſuppoſition to our preaching, people being inſtructed in it from their youth: and the primitive miracles are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally embraced for true. Secondly; there is plentifull proviſion in the ordinary providence of God, and then I know no ground for any faith to expect a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous ſupply. Suppoſe any of our Adverſaries preach to <hi>Welchmen,</hi> being themſelves <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Do not they learne the language? Yet there was the gift
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:166554:15"/> of Tongues. Whether this were a permanent gift or no, I enquire not. If not, the Apoſtles ſure uſed humane induſtry when they preached to people of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language. Healing was a gift; yet, I hope a Chriſtian may ſtudy Phyſick. Then for Heathens, &amp; Miracles being requiſite for a teſtimony to them, conſider that there is rationall morall evidence, for the Goſpel-truth and Chriſtianity comes not with that diſadvantage, being a religion of a great part of the World. Miracles beſide being then neceſſary, the more for the inconſiderableneſſe of the Revealers in their perſons, and the paucity of the Profeſſours; a few contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men in outward appearance contradicting all the reſt of the World. I ſhall only adde, 1. That a great part of the Apoſtles knowledge was by attendance upon Chriſt and converſe with him, and from his expounding the Scriptures after his reſurrection, i. e. in a way of humane diligence and induſtry. 2. Where ever God found gifts, he made uſe of them, as in S. <hi>Paul,</hi> without any ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous repeating the ſame by extraordinary endowments; which further proves that the primitive gifts were many of them for a ſupply to the Apoſtles illiterate education, who though called in Ignorance, were ſent out with the reality and eminency of Learned Accompliſhments.</p>
            <p n="6">6. What Learning S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks againſt, is condemned by Learning it ſelf. Philoſophy, or the then-Philoſophy, oppoſed Reaſon as well as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. The place of <hi>Col.</hi> 2. anſwers it ſelf. Philoſophy according to the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men and the principles of the World, the Philoſophy of the Sects, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicall quirks &amp; ſubtilties and ungrounded dreams and fancies concerning Angels and the like, is nothing to genuine Philoſophy proceeding upon true principles of nature, i. e. God's diſcovery of himſelf to our underſtandings by the light of Reaſon and works of Creation. The Sophiſticall, captious and wrangling deceit, this that is called Philoſophy but indeed was vain deceit, is as much declaimed againſt by the ſober Philoſophers of the ſame Age. Nay, what better morall proviſion in purſuance of the Apoſtles caution, not to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by vain Philoſophicall deceit, then for Miniſters to be well able to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to people the cunning Sophiſtry and deluſion of men that thus delight to lead captive the multitude? Then for the glarous, painted and ranting Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick of thoſe times, if uſed in the matters of God, it offends againſt the main principle of Rhetorick to keep a <hi>decorum</hi> and ſpeak ſuteably to the matter. Lofty towrings of fancy, fawning words, and vainly-garniſh'd expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, neither fitting the capacity of a popular audience, nor becoming the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of a God and the nobility of Divine revelation. Yet true raiſedneſs of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, a majeſticall ſtate, and artificiall and genuine inſinuations, with moſt patheticall captivatings of the minde, are obvious in Scripture: as obvious as fantaſticall cloud-reachings are affectedly frequent in our new Formaliſts Enthuſiaſm, who are truly thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 18.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:166554:16"/> 7. All Learning is advantageous, a great deal neceſſary to an able publiſher of the Truth and Governour of the Church. Tongues, and the gift of Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Utterance, with skill to collect from Scripture eaſily ſpeak their neceſſity. Obſerve here, there are ſome things common to a Miniſter and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar employments; and to this no wonder if ſecular and humane abilities be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Thus, to be able to ſpeak aptly, intelligibly, conſequently, and ſute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to the diſpoſition and capacity of his hearers, is the Apoſtolicall way of preaching: and yet it is the method of ſecular Oratory. Dependance of Truth upon Truth, Concluſions upon Principles is diſcoverable in Scripture revelation, and is of the ſame nature that is in other Sciences, proceeding in the way of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall light acting upon and in revealed Truth. Scripture is writing, and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-interpretation proceeds by the generall rules of interpretation of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, with whom it partakes likewiſe in Language, and helps to underſtand the ſenſe. For my part, I know no one piece of true and reall (whether ſolid or delightfull) Learning that hath not conſiderable advantage in it to the rendering a Miniſter more able to underſtand, explain and confirm the truth of Chriſtian Religion. To be able to ſearch into the true and naturall ſenſe of Apoſtolicall writings, to diſcern the excellency, conſonancy and true authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickneſſe of Scripture, to examine and draw conſequences from it, to ſee the agreement of reaſon and revelation, to view the appearances of God amongſt the Heathen, their ſelf-condemnedneſſe, atteſtations to part of truth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiveneſſe, to take notice of God in the Creation, and diſtinguiſh miracles from impoſtures, to obſerve God's Providence in the World and Church, to ſee the ſeverall breakings forth of light and overcaſtings of darkneſſe in the Church, to make out the Truth by full evidence, to explain and order the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Truths of revelation, and have a diſtinct and more then popular notion of them, ſo as to be able to anſwer Atheiſticall and unbelieving cavills, to converſe with Chriſtians in all Ages and make uſe of their experiences and diſcoveries, to know God, our ſelves, and men in order to a convenient application of our ſelves unto them for their good: theſe are ſome of the ends of Learning, that thus and otherwiſe enlarges, quickens and imbetters the naturall faculties of the Soul. And if all this contains any thing of uſefulneſſe to a Miniſter of the Goſpel, we may ſafely adde that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion</hi> IV. The Univerſities, or places that offer opportunity, advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and encouragement to humane Learning, and that conjoined with and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to Divinity, are ſo farr from being Antichriſtian, that they are of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent neceſſity to the Church of Chriſt. And truly weigh but the concernment of Chriſtian Religion to the peace and happineſſe of a Nation, there can be (to ſay no more) no greater prudence in a Magiſtrate (much more if profeſſing eminency in Chriſtian Religion) then to lay it ſelf out in all juſt and lawfull
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:166554:16"/> means for the conſerving and propagating of it; encouraging and helping forward thoſe who devote their time and ſtudies to be thus ſerviceable to their Countrey.</p>
            <p>I ſhall anſwer but two objections. 1. The Idleneſſe and Luxury of the Univerſity. 2. The diverſity of Opinions and Errours.</p>
            <p>To the Firſt, It is no great wonder, if in theſe times of Liberty, when the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and diſcipline of the Univerſity hath been weakned by ſome ſuch ſpirits amongſt us as our Adverſaries, when Learning ſeems to moſt to be in ſo deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a condition, not much wonder if there be ſome miſcarriages in ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of Youth, which is very ſeldome conſiderate, and hath hot bloud to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe. But I call all that know <hi>Cambridge</hi> (and I queſtion not but others can teſtifie as much for <hi>Oxford)</hi> all that judge by nothing of faction and prejudice, that there is no collection of men this day in <hi>England,</hi> that can ſhew more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent examples of true Worth, reall, ſober Piety and Religion, then are in our Univerſity. Nor are the enormities ſo many or ſo unſuppreſs'd by diſcipline, as diſcontent and malice would bear the World in belief.</p>
            <p>To the Second, I wondered to hear ſuch an argument; You Scholars cannot agree in the truth: <hi>Ergo</hi> what need Univerſities? It is a ſtrange accuſation, that we are a Society of Men. We confeſſe we ſeek after truth, and if we erre, it is becauſe we are fallible. Nay, that we differ, is an argument that we ſet our ſelves to ſeek the truth, and not lazily conſpire in that which, for ought we can tell certainly, may be abſolute falſehood: which is all, I doubt, a perfect unity of opinion will amount to, till it be the fruit of an univerſall infallibility of ſpirit. Rather the ingenuity of an indifferent and free enquiry into Truth, is true Nobleneſſe. I am ſure it is the likelieſt way to diſcover Truth, to have contrary opinions debated here, where there are men able to ſee how farre each agree with other and how much they differ, and to examine each other's grounds: Learning too having civiliz'd their ſpirits to calme and moderate debates, without any thing of that paſſionate heart-burning and inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terateneſſe, which accompanies diſpute among common people. I am ſure the enemies of Learning are at a farre greater diſtance, bateing their joint-perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of the Miniſtery and Scholars. We can pitty them, but not fear them, whileſt next to the Providence of God, with thankfull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of our protection, we dare commit our ſelves fully to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of our wiſe and worthy Governours: appealing in the mean time, for the uſefulneſſe of our Univerſities in the preſent conſtitution, to all whom <hi>Avarice, Envy,</hi> or <hi>Fanatick Frenzy</hi> have not perfectly blinded.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
